<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands monarchy asserted, and proved to be the freest state, and the best common-wealth throughout the world. With a word to the present authority, and His Excellency General Monck.</title>
            <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1016_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203179</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863233</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863233</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 150:E1016[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands monarchy asserted, and proved to be the freest state, and the best common-wealth throughout the world. With a word to the present authority, and His Excellency General Monck.</title>
                  <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W.G. for Richard Lowndes at the White Lion in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Sir Edmund Pierce.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 8 1659"; the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is a blank.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Albemarle, George Monck, --  Duke of, 1608-1670 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115423:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Englands MONARCHY Aſſerted, and Proved TO BE <hi>The FREEST STATE,</hi> AND <hi>The BEST COMMON-WEALTH</hi> Throughout the World. WITH A WORD to the Preſent Authority, AND His EXCELLENCY GENERAL <hi>MONCK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> for <hi>Richard Lowndes</hi> at the <hi>White Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115423:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115423:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Englands Monarchy</hi> Aſſerted and proved to be the <hi>Freeſt State</hi> and Beſt <hi>Common-wealth</hi> throughout the World.</head>
            <head>With a <hi>Word</hi> to the preſent Authority, and his Excellency Gen. <hi>MONCK.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow doth the Preſs labour (in this Scribling age) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen which is put upon it, by every wilde and brain-ſick fancy of our Republican Candidates; each of them, according to the length of that Worm which is crawling in his head, flinging in his Paper myte, though of never ſo baſe and counterfeit ſtuff, towards the erection of that, which is ſuppoſed in his opinion, but to look like matter of Defence, for this <hi>Utopian</hi> thing, of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> ſo much noyſed and talked on amongſt us, Though to ſober and judicious perſons, It cannot but be known, that the leaſt blaſt proceeding from unbyaſſed, ſolid, and impartial truth, and prudence, ſcatters (as to us of this Nation) all thoſe empty Nothings which ſeem to make ſuch a fine and Gawdy ſhew, into meer ayr and bubble: For, let the pyth and ſubſtance of all, even the beſt of that matter (for ſome there is ſo frothy and full of filth that the very reading of it nauſeates) that hath been ſaid or writ on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be pickt out, and but narrowly ſurvey'd and conſidered, and what doth it all amount to, more, than what (as it relates to us) the apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one ſhort Diſtinction, takes off the edge of all in it, which looks like any thing of Logick or Senſe. It may ſurely be acknowledged, That, It is poſſible, a People may live happily enough, under any of the three chief forms mentioned in Story, viz. <hi>Monarchy, Ariſtocracy,</hi> or <hi>Democracy,</hi> ſo they have good Laws, and good Magiſtrates. The form in that caſe, doth not perhaps much add, or diminiſh; But to prefer any of the two laſt, before the firſt, is to deny that faith and experience which all good Hiſtory hath taught us; And, as the caſe ſtands in this Nation, where Monarchy is more ancient than Hiſtory it ſelf, and ſo venerable and acceptable to the ſpirit and genius of the whole body of the People, of all ſorts, our Laws (the abſolutely beſt in the Chriſtian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115423:3"/> world) being graffed into that ſtock, and having their birth and bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding under that happy Government, To attempt, or any way affect, the Deſired alteration, were nought elſe but to Renounce and bid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to our reaſon and underſtanding. Were we a people newly Dropt from the Clouds, and now to begin the ſetling of a frame of Government for our ſelves, The beſt Directions, we could gather from all that hath hitherto been ſaid, or indeed poſſibly can be excogitated, by the wit and invention of man, to recommend us to that, which ſome perſons for their vile and ugly intereſt and ends ſo much hanker after, hath their whole fabrick built upon ſuch ſuppoſitions as no rational or prudent man can poſſibly ſuppoſe all arguments for it; Taking for granted, That, which never was, is, or indeed can be ſound, amongſt men clothed with corrupt Mortality: But when we are already under ſuch a conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution as is premiſed, and which is the chief matter of the ſubſequent Diſcourſe, To ravel all our Laws, Dig up ſuch ancient Foundations, and unſettle that firm Bottom, which hath for ſo many ages rendred us an opulent, famous and flouriſhing people: It would be ſuch a peece of folly and madneſs, That any Potent neighbour Prince, may ſurely have juſt cauſe to think that by the Law of Nations he may invade and poſſeſs our properties, upon the Title, ſcore, and accompt of Idiotiſm, Lunacy, or Phrenſie.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible, That ſome (otherwiſe very eminent and worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) may by the ſubtilties and inſinuations of others, be ſo far miſlead, as to think very gloriouſly of that which is ſo much talked on, and ſo little underſtood, <hi>A Free State,</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> and that the true and real eſſentials thereof cannot be had, and enjoyed, but in, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a popular frame and conſtitution as they fancy. Theſe ſubtle men know well enough, that there is no eaſier way to cheat us out of our beſt condition, than by the hopes of enjoying it in a better manner, and under a fuller freedome: And ſome of them know alſo, as well as the beſt ſort of their bribed Pen-men, That there is a great and vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the form of a thing, and the eſſence of it; The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding and not diſtinguiſhing whereof, in our conſiderations upon that ſubject: But being ſo preſented, as if the one were not to be had without the other, is that, which gives them ſuch advantage to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their corrupt and crafty beguilings to ſuch upon whoſe capacities and underſtandings they have hope to impoſe and prevail: And although their owne ſiniſter and vitious ends therein, is ſo manifeſt and notorious, every body knowing well their inclination, temper, and diſpoſition, and what it is, they hereby aim at, <hi>viz.</hi> Not to be in the leaſt hazard or fear of puniſhment, or reſtitution, for whatſoever acted or rapin'd by them, during the late ſhakings and convulſions of the Times; for though they are or may be undoubtedly aſſured, of an obſolute and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain indempnity, and a full and free injoying of what they are ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be deprived of, yet (oh the fright and terrour of a guilty Soul!)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115423:3"/> That will not ſerve the turn, They cannot reſt in quier, nor in joy any calm thoughts; unleſs they tare up all by the roots, and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh all footſteps of that Government and thoſe Laws, which may in any ſort continue the leaſt of fear, hazard, or danger upon them: And whatever other fair and ſpecious pretences are made, of a <hi>Free State,</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and other glorious and gloſſy things, to delude and captivate vulgar apprehenſions; Yet their own conſciences cannot but tell them, That from this corrupt ſtem and root alone, ſprings all theſe fine, Gawdy and Republican leaves and bloſſomes; For this is openly manifeſt, That whilſt ſome Grandees of this ſort ſat tat he ſtern, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their diſcords in all other things were almoſt infinite, yet they ſtill agreed in this, to deſtroy our fundamentals in order to complete their deſigns, and ſecure there own empty and pannick fears and je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies; which ingaged all ſober and judicious perſons, to deteſt their way and courſes, and more firmly unite themſelves, to the true loyal intereſt, at abhorring thoſe violent confuſions, and deſtracting altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, amongſt us, which they ſaw this <hi>Free ſtate</hi> or Republick muſt of neceſſity introduce: Now, that this their fallacies, of thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunding the formalities, and eſſentials, of a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> together; And inſinuating the non-poſſibility, as it were, of the one to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other, may the more clearly and fully appear: Let us reflect a while upon the Government here amongſt us, as it ſtood twenty years ago; which though truly Monarchical, yet did it by a frequent Refining of it ſelf upon ſeveral occaſions (rejecting the evil, and retaining the good of all the known beſt Governments in the world) raiſe it ſelf to ſuch a mirrour of perfection, That it became the envy of <hi>Monarchies,</hi> and ſhame of all <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> who therein might behold themſelves ſo ecclipſed and ſilenced in all the pretentions to Liberty and Freedom; That it might be truly aſſerted of us, That with the moſt Choyce and ſignal ornaments of the Nobleſt Kingdomes, we injoyed all the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities and Priviledges, of <hi>A Free State,</hi> and <hi>Common wealth.</hi> And although All nations have their ſeveral and peculiar Rights and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, yet none ſo truely free as the people of <hi>England,</hi> can they be but ſo happy, as to keep their fundamental Laws inviolate and unſhaken.</p>
            <p>The Excellency of theſe our Rights and Freedoms, confiſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in theſe Particulars following,
<list>
                  <item>1. That we cannot be diſſeized or charged in our Freeholds, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes, or Goods, but by Law, or our own conſent; and that in a Free and lawful Parliament, and for the publick good onely.</item>
                  <item>2. There is ſuch care taken of the Liberty and Freedom of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, That none ought to be ſtraitned or impriſoned but by a lawful Magiſtrate. The cauſe of the impriſonment is to be expreſſed in the warrant, and proſecution within a fit time to be made, or the party to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115423:4"/> be delivered by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> which the Judge cannot deny; and if anundue or illegal commitment be made, it is actionable at Law, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Officers who are inſtrumental therein.</item>
                  <item>3. That no Law hath force to bind, but ſuch as by our own allowance, hath been or ſhall be eſtabliſhed, by the ſoveraign of the Nation, or elſe hath beenreceived <hi>ab antiquo</hi> by the conſtant uſage of the People.</item>
                  <item>4. No Judgment concludes us but ſuch as is paſſed be ore Magiſtrates, of our own nation, who ought to be ordinarily called, duly authorized, and legally ſworn to do us juſtice according to the known Laws of the Land.</item>
                  <item>5. All our proceedings and Trials at Law ought to he publick, to our greateſt eaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> in the open view of the County, Hundred, Society, or Corporation, where the cauſe of action is ſuppoſed to be given.</item>
                  <item>6. Every particular perſon in matter of Crime or intereſt is Triable onely <hi>per pares,</hi> his equals, fellows, or Neighbours, who make the ſaid Trial upon their corporal oath, from which form of Trial, (in point of right) the Soveraign himſelf cannot plead exemption.</item>
                  <item>7. That Juſtice according to Law, and that form of Trial, cannot be ſold, delayed, or denyed to any perſon whatſoever.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief heads of the Rights, Freedoms, and Liberties of the People of this Nation firmly ſetled and eſtabliſhed, under Monarchy, which together with other particulars, collectable out of that above thirty times confirmed <hi>Magna charta,</hi> and the Petition of Right, and what were granted by the late King, in his laſt and never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Parliament, ſure ſuch a ſtock of Immunity and Freedom for a people, that all the Free-ſtates, and Common-wealths, that are, or ever were, extant, in any place throughout the whole univerſe, may be juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged to ſhew if they can, the like Liberty and Freedom for their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Subjects: We may truly ſay, that the Peoples Liberty walks with equal pace at leaſt, and ſtands upon as firm if not firmer ground, than the Soveraigns Prerogative, nor are they eſteemed leſs tender and ſacred; For upon the leaſt infringement, or violation of what belongs to the people, in point of Liberty and Immunity, far more loud alarms have been alwayes given to the whole Nation, Then have been taken by Soveraigntive, when the very bowels of Prerogative have been deeply gaſhed, and in a manner quite torn out.</p>
            <p>Some experience, we have of late years had, of a Common-wealth (as it was called) here amongſt us, <hi>viz.</hi> from 1648, to 1653, and ſtrange unknown Guardians it had ſet over it, and as ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of acts of violence, and arbitrary exorbitancy; It was moſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently guilty of, ſuch as have cauſe enough to be by all remembred, and ſurely cannot eaſily be forgotten; And ſo, though in a very faint and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering condition, it continued acting its illegal cruelties, upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and that with all ſeverity, until that fate befell it; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to moſt of that ſort, and kind, though of far better frame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115423:4"/> than can poſſibly be ever expected amongſt us, which is, that unleſs it can Truckle under ſome potent Neighbour Prince, ſhall be ſure to be invaded by Uſurpation, debauched by Oligarchy, or confounded by Anarchy: And this, how often ſince, it hath in this ſhort time been our own caſe, it may with ſadneſs enough be remembred by us; For how is it probable, or indeed poſſibly to be expected, that any Government e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and eſtabliſhed by inequality and force (as ours muſt needs be, if we deſert our old foundation) can ever ſubſiſt and faſten, without an exorbicant and all-devouring power, and force to uphold and maintain it; And on whoſe ſhoulders the burthen of that muſt needs lye, (the grand and ſtanding Treaſury and Revenue being exhauſted, and ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred into private hands, and all publick Monies (or rather indeed Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines) paſſing through the pitchy claws of ſuch State harpies as we have already had experience of, and ſuch or their like as cannot but be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected hereafter) it is eaſie enough to be conjectured; In which, and manifold other reſpects, It is impoſſible to be imagined otherwiſe in reaſon, but that the little fingers of our upſtart Lords and Staeſ-men, of ſuch an empty new-riſing State (be the <hi>Rota,</hi> or whymſical wheel terning or ſtanding ſtill) cannot poſſibly but prove more heavy and weighty to a tame and tired people, then the whole loyns of a Free born Heir, and of an ancient Monarchy ſetled as this is, whoſe Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Title, and Self-ſufficiency, will be <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> enough to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples diſcharge, of whatſoever may but look like oppreſſion to them: And ſhould we after all our expence, Toile, Torments of faction, and ſuch emptying of our ſelves, fix and ſettle at length, into ſuch a degree of poſſible permanency, as that we may but ſeem to ſtand a high-lone, though with the prop of an army (For that in no caſe muſt be left out) what Alarms and excitements ſhould we preſently give to all our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, by our new upſtart and ſtrange ſhape? What State ſoloeſciſme ſhould we be guilty of, and very probable provocations to all our beſt Allies? And their being ſeveral Dormant accompts, in the memorials of Princes abroad, who watch but for their opportunity and advantage, can it in reaſon or prudence be otherwiſe imagined, but that in the concluſion, we muſt be forced to admit of theirs, or at beſt our own Soveraigns con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon us: Beſides, how will our <hi>State-craſtsmen</hi> ſodder up the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, about thoſe two ancient Monarchies of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> And whether they will be long contented (if at all) to Truckle under ſuch a half, (or rather no) headed Bedſted as ours is like to be, and that without either Curtaines or Valence to it, when they may have a rich and royal Canopy, and Cloth of State of their own, That would ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do well to be enquired into, and to have us aſſured of.</p>
            <p>By what is premiſed, we may ſomewhat gueſſe at the cheat which would be put upon us, by thoſe partially Byaſſed, and ſelf-intereſſed men, who make this noyſe and ſtir by themſelves and their hyred Advocates, of all ſorts, ſubtle, and ſilly, about this buſineſſe of a Common-wealth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115423:5"/> which will be more illuſtrated upon farther contemplation of that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe which we and our Anceſtors have ſo long enjoyed, under that Celeſtial form of Government <hi>(Monarchy)</hi> our Lives, Liberties and Eſtates being under it, ſo well and amply ſecured by our Lawes, that what people was there under Heaven, that might with truth and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, boaſt of a more flouriſhing and happy condition than we were in, till Ambition and Faction entred amongſt us, and rent and tore in pieces, all the Gards and Seams, which linkt and bound us together, and which adorned and filled us with ſuch beauty, health, vigor and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, that we were become the envy and wonder of the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world. And that which hath been by thoſe rotten, and ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed men, ſo often imputed to Monarchy, and King ſhip, (Tyranny) ſo faſt and ſtrongly tyed and chained up by our Lawes, from doing hurt or prejudice to us, in our beſt and deereſt concerns, that we were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, even dainty, nice and wanton in our felicities; ſuch a <hi>Cornu Copia,</hi> or <hi>Catholicon,</hi> of welfare, and happineſſe, our Prince and Soveraignes gentle power was to us, that whilſt it enjoyed its juſts Rights, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thence all the benefits of plenty, eaſe, and quiet, that poſſibly could be imagined. It was our curb to Tumults, our Moderator to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, our Sanctuary for Remedies of all ſorts, our aſſured preventer of Miſchiefs, it topp'd Uſurpation, adminiſtred Juſtice, afforded Equity, and indulged Clemency and Mercy: It was the very joy of our Hearts, and the breath of our Noſtrils, and what is it but a kinde of black, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous, and miſcheivous Envy (had I ſaid Blaſphemy, there is good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it in Holy Writ) to deſpiſe, reject, and kick againſt it, and ſo againſt Heaven it ſelfe. Monarchy being the ſole and onely Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordained by God, and Kings and Kingdomes, his alone inſtitution and planting, as is cleer by the whole current of Sacred Scripture, from <hi>Adam</hi> even till the Primitive Church after Chriſt; and Republiques, States, and ſuch like, a meer depraved Inſtitution of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, for corrupt and ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ends; and as it was, and is eſtabliſhed here amongſt us, ſo bounded by Law, and exempt from Tyranny, that it could not ſo much as oppreſſe a poor harmleſs Orphan. No Sheriffe, Conſtable, or Bailiffe, but was more terrible, powerfull, and petulant, in their ſeverall and diſtinct wayes and powers, than the Soveraigne himſelf, and leſs ſubject to the curb, rule, and guidance of Law, in moſt of their actions and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations: He neither made Lawes in his perſonall capacity, neither did he execute or interpret them. No Judge ſtood in awe of his ſingle command, to juſtifie the leaſt treſpaſs. Nothing was more true than that great and general Maxime, <hi>That the King could do no wrong;</hi> for in the coſe of any wrong done, the preſumption of Law was, That he did it not, but his Officers or Agents were accomptable, and reſponſal to the Law for it; his Power was ſo limited by his Juſtice, that his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure could ſtreighten no mans liberty, but the Law would relieve him by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> which the Judge durſt not deny. And yet this ends,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115423:5"/> Innocuous, meek and gentle Authority, for the vile, baſe, and corrupt ends, of ſome bloody, covetous, and ambitious perſons, muſt be branded with the odious name of Tyranny, and all the filth that can be caſt up from their Rankerous Lungs muſt be flung upon it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, a Negative voice the Soveraigne had in the paſſing of Laws, but what (upon due conſideration) did it ſignifie, but a meer weapon of defence, to ſhield the Goverument from being proſtituted to altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at the will and pleaſure of inferiority. And doth not late times tell us, there was a juſt neceſſity for it? and was there not ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent awe and power in the People for this Negative voice, that as they could paſs no Law without him, ſo could not he without them? beſides, was not the publick purſe in their hands, and diſpoſe, to engage him to paſs what they had a minde to? Were not all the Officers, and Miniſters of State, and others, appointed by him, accomptable to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and to the Laws? or was it in his power to ſave any of them, or yeild him the leaſt skreen, ſhelter or protection, in caſe they ſtood obnoxious. The Militia and Nations Sword he wore indeed, for decency ſake only, but could not draw it for the oppreſſion of the People, but by their own conſents, he having no mercenary Redcoats at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but the Armes of the Nation were in the hands of men of Eſtate and intereſt, the Officers being Gentlemen commonly of the better ſort and quality, and the Soldier a Yeomen or Farmer at leaſt. All of them ſuch, as cannot in reaſon be conceived to joyne againſt Law, with the Luſt and Ambition (could ſuch a thing poſſibly be) of any ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what quality ſoever, to abridge and deſtroy any juſt Freedome, they enjoyed as their Birth-right.</p>
            <p>This was the ſtate and condition of the Militia, and Armes and Force of the Nation, in thoſe happy dayes of exerciſed Monarchy amongſt us, which right or wrong, be the truth what it will, and never ſo manifeſt and notoriouſly known to be ſo, yet muſt, and ſhall by ſome, be ſtill called Tyrannical; whereas ever ſince theſe bleſsed Halcion times, how have we found the caſe to be altered in that, and all other particulars, ſince this Rumble of a Free State, and Common-wealth hath brolled in our heads, eſpecially when Fanatick Saintſhip and profeſſion came in to bear ſway amongſt us? And the Good old Cauſe-mongers brought in their Canting Tones, and Phraſes, which, like Gipſies, they uſed to know one anothers mindes by, whilſt they munged the peoples Noſes, and publiquely pickt their pockets. What ſtrange and unheard of violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and outrages have our eyes beheld committed by thoſe, who under ſuch bare our Armes, and were paid for it by us, and in ſtead of protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and defence to us, as in the dayes of our Monarchy duly exerciſed? what awe, dread and terror, did ſuch keep the whole Nation under, from the higheſt to the loweſt, of all ſorts and qualities?</p>
            <p>But why is that mentioned, which is in a manner the leaſt of perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and a kind of a <hi>Peccadillo,</hi> to thoſe many other grand and piacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115423:6"/> Crimes and Offences, Rapines, Murthers, hideous and unparallel'd oppreſſions of all all ſorts and kinds, which have been our lot and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ever ſince we were made ſo unhappy, as to be deprived of our old Government, and Royal Race of Governours, and became ſlaves and bondmen to a generation of ſuch State Empericks, pretending cure and healing to thoſe wounds, which themſelves (for curſed ambitious ends) had made; As that certainly none then we, have more rightly imitated the Dog in the fable, That have loſt the ſubſtance of an opulent flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and happy Free State and Comm-wealth, which really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we injoyed in all its eſſentials, and perfections, and caught, and embraced onely, an empty ſhadow, and ſound of one in our ears (which (whatever may be pretended) is all we are ever like to enjoy, under any Government but our old one) when our Eſtates, Liberties, Bodies, Lives; nay, our very Souls have been, Torn, Heraſſed, Oppreſſed, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chered, and Tortured, under the ſeveral viciſſitudes, of all the moſt Tyrannical inſolent and boundleſs powers of unlimited arbitrary uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, that ever ſhewed themſelves in any age or place, amongſt the Sons of Chriſtian men: And which are yet by theſe men (who and what ſort and principles they are of, is manifeſt enough) laboured and endevoured to be continued amongſt us, under the ſame ſpetious Title, Name, and Shew of a Free Stare and Common-wealth, whoſe ſhadow muſt ſtill upon all occaſions be freſhly aſſumed, though the ſubſtance, Themſelves know we have already in the beſt manner and moſt abſolute perfection, anciently and firmly ſetled and eſtabliſhed amongſt us, by onr Laws: But ſhould they as formerly be in any ſort returning upon us, in what ſhape ſoever (for let the outſide be what it will, it is very well known what lies within, and what fruits and effects muſt needs be thence produced) It is hoped almighty God will ſo unite and animate the Nation with ſuch a noble publick ſpirit, That our ancient and known ſundamental Laws, and in them, the peace, quiet weifate, and happineſs of our Countrey, may (next our duty to him) find the chiefeſt place in our hearts and minds, and arm us with a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folution and und aunted zeal and courage, to uſe all juſt and lawful means, that this Divine Providence ſhall hold forth and ſeaſon to our hands, for theirs and in them our ſelf preſervation, that we may ſhew, we have derived from our progenitors a true Engliſh Gallantry, defying all Hazards and Dangers in diſcharge of our Duties to God, our Laws, and our Countrey: Nor can any man be juſtly eſteemed worthy, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his fathers Honours, Immunities, and Freedoms, who dures not convey them through all Difficulties and Dangers, to ſucceeding generations.</p>
            <p>And that this reſolution may be firmly-fixed upon the ſpirits of thoſe now in place and power. It is alſo hoped, that it will not by them be deemed nought and unſeaſonable to hint to them this <hi>Memorandum,</hi> or Quere, whether from the firſt beginning of that great conteſt, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115423:6"/> between the late King and his Oppoſers; There was not any thing more chiefly and principally all along inſiſted upon, by both parties, than the upholding and maintaining the ancient known and fundamental laws of the Land? Was not the pretended violation and infringement of them, urged againſt thoſe two great <hi>Zanzummines</hi> of Church and State, the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Strafford;</hi> And urges ſo far, as that their lives were layed down and ſacrificed, for thoſe laws, maintenance, and preſervation; and hath not the ſwerving and devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from thoſe Laws, let in all thoſe floods and torrents of Rapine, Miſery, and Calamity, with which ſuch an inundation have ſo long overſpread the the face of this our Iſle, and its dominions, and every where fill'd the ſame with horror and confuſion; And is not this ſo cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt, and notoriouſly known, that the light it ſelf that dayly ſhines amongſt us, may by mortal power be ſooner totally extinguiſhed, than that undoubted truth; Nay, hath not this truth been often hinted and remembred by themſelves, as may be ſeen in their printed publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by way of vindication of themſelves, concerning their ſecleſion from the place and authority they are now in, with a cry and clamour to thoſe then in power, to heal the ſores and waſting diviſions of the Nation, by a Reinduction of the known ancient and fundamental Laws thereof; and are not theſe things, and much more to this purpoſe, which may be truly aſſerted, but of yeſterday, as it were, and very freſh and recent in the minds and memories of all men? how then may or can it any way be anſwered to God, our Saviour, and the world, by thoſe now in authority, if after all this, and ſo ſad and lamentable an experience made, and the care of all our doleſul maladies, ſo cleerly apparent, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by no other, or better remedy, than by a continuance of the firm eſtabliſhing of thoſe Laws; And that remedy be plain and eaſie to be layed hold on, ſhould they at ſuch a time as this, be terrified, or upon any pretence whatſoever, be ſo far ſeduced, as to delay and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſame, or to put any bars or ſhackles upon the freedome, liberties, and birthrights of the people, ſo, or in that manner, as the ſame may be any way hindered or impeded; Nay, themſelves alſo being cryed out too, and clamoured on, for this, by the general and univerſal vote, and earneſt deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the whole body of the Nations, of all ſorts, conditions and qualities; And whatſoever the Intereſt be which ſeems to oppoſe it, as it is ſiniſter, corrupt, and vitious, in its firſt being and origination, ſo is it odious and ſacrilegious to God, and vile and contemptible, even in the eyes of the world, which it ſo much looks upon and reſpects; and however ſome of that Intereſt (for there are two ſorts of them, one far more moderate, peaceful, and modeſt, than the other) would have the ſame thought to be of that bulk and magnitude, as thence to raiſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, in its favour, that may keep the wound ſtill open, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral peace either altogether unſetled, or done Republicanly, and ſo ſlightly infirmly, and not laſtingly, ſo as that there may be ſtill hopes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115423:7"/> left for them, of new booty and prey to be further obtained, and added to their former heap of ſpoils and devourings; Yet upon due ſearch made, It will undoubtedly be found, that ſuch of that Intereſt, who are thus minded, and ſo far intoxicated with its poyſon, as to deſire a new foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, for our Laws to ſettle on, and ſo labour and endevour the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the old, and introducing a novel frame, and conſtitution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, are ſo thin and tentious, and ſo contemptibly inconſiderable a number, and moſt or all of them likewiſe, having ſuch deep ſtains upon them (to ſay no more) that it cannot but be thought the moſt deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of all miſeries, and calamities, that can befal a people and nation, nay three nations, and the numerous people thereof, And a ſtrange kind of infatuation of that Authority over them, that any ſuch care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould be had and taken, for ſuch a ſort, and ſuch an Intereſt, That the conſideration thereof, ſhould any way obſtruct and hinder, that firm and laſting ſettlement, which concerns ſo many millions of perſons, of all ſorts, ſexes, qualities, and conditions, and which is ſo woven into, and concentered in our Laws, and the very vital part of them, and of all our liberties, freedoms, and happineſſe, which began likewiſe with the firſt natives of this Iſland the <hi>Brittains,</hi> and continued amongſt us, for ſo many centuries of years, and recieved its approbation, by ſo many Ages and Generations of our Fore-fathers, and Anceſtors, and rendred us a famous and flouriſhing People and Nation throughout the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>Nor need either of theſe ſort of men be at all doubtful neither (what ver vain and empty jealouſies and fears they have to the contrary) But upon ſuch a juſt and righteous ſettlement, of a firm and laſting peace, the wiſdom of the Nation may, and no doubt but will, find out a way and means, That not a man of-them ſhall be a penny damnified in their purchaſes and acquiſitions of any ſort or kind whatſoever: And yet both Crown and Church have a fitting and full patrimony too; which (when it comes to that) may with as much eaſe be demoliſhed to any capable underſtanding, as this expreſſion thereof is here ſet down to be read and peruſed: And if this be ſo, as to them, which clearly and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controverſie may (and that without much difficulty) be done, and no mans property intrencht upon, nor the publick body of the nation at all prejudiced or damnified; And the Church controverſies by a national and legal Synod convened in due form, appeaſed, quieted and ſetled, ſo as no truly tender Chriſtian conſcience, may at all be impoſed upon: But have that due evangelical liberty, which may in any kind, by the moſt ſacred holy Writ be allowed, (And further, it is ſuppoſed no ſober Chriſtian will deſire) what ſhould hinder if the work were once ſtrenuouſly, faithfully, and impartially ſet upon: But that yet we might hope for ſo much mercy from Heaven, as that after all theſe tempeſtuous ſtormy violences, rending waſting and conſuming diviſions, doleful and deplorable miſeries and calamities, which have ſo long,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115423:7"/> and ſo fiercely raved, and raged amongſt us. The Almighties hand may cloſe up all our breaches, and we enjoy the bleſſed and happy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, of a well eſtabliſhed firm and laſting peace; It is likewiſe hoped, that there is nothing premiſed in this paper, which may in any kind give offence to any now in place and power, either as to matters civil, or to that worthy and noble military General, by whoſe power &amp; prudence much of our miſeries have bin already releaſed, and in whom it is by moſt believed there is ſuch a generous and publick Ayre, and Spirit for the good and welfare of the Church and Nation; that however the mindes of ſome pious, ſober, and judicious perſons, are much flatted and dejected by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall particulars, which have paſſed and become publick; yet he being extricated and quitted, from the poyſonous intoxications, of ſome very viperous Spirits, and the ſubtle and crafty inſinuations of others, who, though not altogether ſo bad, yet much corrupted and miſled by ſelfeiſh Intereſt and Faction: He will, upon due deliberation, ſeriouſly ſet his heart and thoughts upon the furtherance and advanceing that, and that onely, which may beſt conduce to the firme and laſting ſettlement of the peace, and quiet of a torn, tattered, and tyred people, whom he found plunged, and weltring in their own wretched and deplorable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and calamities. And as he hath had the honour to ſerve faithfully, the conjunct intereſt of his Soveraigne, and the Nation in his former imployments, ſo he will not be now induced to ſever them upon any cauſe, ſpecious ſhew, or pretence whatſoever: For be it what it will be, that is inſiſted upon, to move him to affect ſuch a partition and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration (come it cloathed in what ſhape or colour ſoever it will or can come) he may reſt aſſuredly certain, that it comes not without its ſpeciall deſigne upon himſelfe, which, (if not avoided) in the end will be his undoubted utter ruine and deſtruction; let him bring it, <hi>Ad ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium lapidem,</hi> to the true Touch-ſtone, either of Religion, Law, Juſtice, Equity or Policy, and try it by either of theſe, or all theſe together, and ſee, how empty, light, vaine, falſe, and counterfeit it will prove, in all its ſhews and pretences. It is known well enough, that there are ſome perſons (and perhaps from too many of them he hath no few corrupt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers) who are ſo fixed and rivited to a deſire of accompliſhing their own covetous and ambitious ends, though by meanes never ſo vile and ruinous to others: And are by ſelfe-guilt, ſo filled with rankour, envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, againſt that perſon, which by all Law of God, Nature, and the Land, ſhould be ſacred to them; That it is verily believed, that if an Angel or Seraphin from Heaven ſhould appear, to perſwade them to their duty in that particular, they like their ſeat and footing ſo well upon earth, and are ſo taken with the rule and domination, which they fanſie they have floating in their own empty brains, and have ſo ſet up their heart, hopes, and faith upon it, that even ſuch a meſſage from Heaven it ſelfe, ſhould not prevaile upon them. Theſe men, let him pleaſe to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115423:8"/> avoid and ſhun (as to their whiſpers and Councels) as he would ſome noyſome and hideous poyſon, and hearken to the ſober deliberations of the ſolid, judicious, and truly (not hypocritically) pious and moderate. And indeed (next to Almighty God, and his Sacred Word) conſult but his own Soul and Conſcience, which he hath profeſſed, ſtands cleer, and impartial to all Intereſts and Factions, in this great buſineſſe of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; And let not the Publick Genius and Inclination, nay, the hearty and earneſt declared deſire and longing for, of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of all ſorts, and from all parts and places thereof, be deſpicable to him, or ſlighted by him; but as he profeſſeth his endeavours, for the publick ſettlement, ſo let him (declining all private junctoes) be directed therein, by publick advertiſement. It is the whole People and Nations that muſt be obliged, let the whole People and Nations therefore freely be heard: ſhould they deſire in point of Government, (were it now in their choice) that which were not fit for them, if they be not hearkened to, they cannot be engaged: For as no man hath wrong, with his conſent, ſo certainly none in ſuch caſe can be obliged againſt it. The generall and publick deſires of the whole Nation in this particular, is known very well, nor is it doubted, but he will make good what he hath profeſſed, and ſerve their publick true intereſt, and not the private cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt intereſt and ends of ſome few. Many Millions there be on the one ſide, and ſome petty inconſiderable number, not worth naming on the other. Generall Peace, and a firm and laſting ſettlement, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the one ſide; Warre, and diſtracting confuſions, and in the end, general ruine and deſtruction on the other. Many other particulars may be hinted to him, but as he is noble and prudent, ſo it is verily expected, and earneſtly hoped, we ſhall finde anſwerable effects thereof every way from him, and ſuch as ſhall crown him with Riches and honour in this life, and eternall joy and happineſſe in that which is to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115423:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
